<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="printDBI.xsl"?>
<div class='division' id='s0'>
	<div class='chapter' id='title'>

<text class='h1'>Practical  Uses  of the Bible</text> 

<text class='h1'>Bible Memorization</text> 

<text class='p'>Always remember the value of memorizing scripture can neverbe overstated.</text> 
<text class='p'>Why bible memorization so important.</text> 
<text class='p'>It is a means of bible study</text> 
<text class='p'>There are three major methods ofbible study:</text> 
<text class='p'>Bible memorization is a source of ready answers when sharing the truthabout Jesus Christ</text> 
<text class='p'>Be prepared to face all attacks and with the word of godin your heart and mind!!!</text> 
<text class='p'> Rom. 10:15; I Cor.  15:57; II Cor.  1:19; 2:14; 3:19; 10:4-6;Eph.  6:11-17; I John 5:4</text> 
<text class='p'>Bible memory is an aid in knowing God's Will.</text> 
<text class='p'>Scripture clearly reveals what God's Will is.</text> 
<text class='p'>Memorizing Scripture enables us to have an intimate workinggrasp and an understanding of God's Will and Purpose.</text> 
<text class='p'>Memorizing the scripture is the source for strengthening ourfaith.</text> 
<text class='p'>Our faith should be firmly rooted in the facts revealed byGod to us in the bible.  By faith; we can obtain promises, appropriate truthsand obey commands as revealed in scripture.</text> 
<text class='p'> A Help in overcoming temptations Matthew 4:1-11</text> 

<text class='p'>It is imperative that Thus saith the Lord be written uponour mind and heart for immediate recall when our faith is being tested.</text> 

<text class='p'>Bible memorization is a means of insuring proper attitudes</text> 
<text class='p'>Isaiah 26:3</text> 
<text class='p'>If we keep our mind on the Lord by memorizing His Word Hewill keep us in perfect peace in the midst of the heaviest of storms.</text> 

<text class='p'>The resource for purifying our mind with good thoughts ismemorizing the Word of God.</text> 
<text class='p'>BAD-THOUGHT SOLUTION:</text> 
<text class='p'>Philippians 4:8 ... "think on these things"...</text> 

<text class='p'>Bible memorization is the means of gaining strength andcourage.</text> 

<text class='p'>WHAT did God say to Moses?</text> 
<text class='p'>Deut. 1:38; 3:28; 8:317:18-20; 6:6-12</text> 
<text class='p'>WHAT did God say toJoshua?</text> 
<text class='p'>Joshua 1:8; Deut 31:7,23</text> 
<text class='p'>WHAT did Jesus say to His disciples?</text> 
<text class='p'>Mat. 4:4</text> 
<text class='p'>WHAT is the ultimate success?</text> 
<text class='p'>To please the Lord</text> 
<text class='p'>Mat.  3:17; 12:18; 17:5; Mk.  1:11; Lk. 3:22; I Cor.  1:21; Col. 1:19; Heb.  11:5; II Pt. 1:17</text> 

<text class='p'>Everybody can memorizescripture</text> 

<text class='p'>You can memorize scripture!!!</text> 
<text class='p'>Young children can memorize scripture.</text> 
<text class='p'>Deut.  6:6-7</text> 

<text class='p'>How the bible should be memorized.</text> 

<text class='p'>The bible should bestudied and memorized with diligence</text> 
<text class='p'>Realize it.</text> 
<text class='p'>Carry it.</text> 
<text class='p'>Keep them in a prominent place.</text> 
<text class='p'>Understand each verse in its context.</text> 
<text class='p'>Learn new verses in the New Testament.</text> 
<text class='p'>Learn new verses in the Old Testament.</text> 
<text class='p'>Always read the whole verse.</text> 
<text class='p'>Concentrate on one verse.</text> 

<text class='p'>It is a lot easier to memorize and remember a verse if youunderstand it.</text> 

<text class='p'>Memorize each verse don't rephrase it.</text> 

<text class='p'>Keys for memorization</text> 

<text class='p'>The most important key to accurate and lasting Bible memoryis having it word perfect.</text> 

<text class='p'>John 14:26 But the Comforter, which is the Holy Ghost, whomthe Father will send in my name, he shall teach you all things, and bring allthings to your remembrance, whatsoever I have said unto you.</text> 

<text class='p'>An important key is review, review, review, review, review</text> 
<text class='p'>Review daily</text> 
<text class='p'>Use a file card system and look as needed.</text> 
<text class='p'>Quote verses before you go to sleep at night.</text> 
<text class='p'>Repeat verses upon awakening.</text> 
<text class='p'>Read the scripture, write it, read it again, memorize it,read again to make sure that you are memorizing the verse perfectly.</text> 
<text class='p'>Memorize with others.</text> 
<text class='p'>Practice Practice Practice Practice Practice  Practice Practice</text> 
<text class='p'>John 13:17 "If you know these things, and happy and to beenvied are you</text> 
<text class='p'>if you practice them – if you act accordingly and really dothem. " - - AMP.</text> 
<text class='p'>OUR LOVE FOR OTHERS.   John. 13:35</text> 
<text class='p'>OUR FRUITFUL LIVES.   John. 15:08</text> 
<text class='p'>OUR OBEDIENCE TO HIS WORD  John  8:31</text> 

<text class='p'>The Word of God is the Sword of the Spirit to destroy theyoke of bondages caused by sin and false doctrines.</text> 
<text class='p'>Isaiah 10:27; 1 John2:27; Eph.  6:17; Isaiah 59:19; 1 John3:8; John 10:10</text> 










<text class='h1'>Important Vocabulary of the Bible</text> 
<text class='p'><b> Affirm</b> to declare positively, to confirm /claim - to demand as rightfully belonging to one, a right to something.</text> 
<text class='p'><b> Qualifies</b> makes fit for a job.  (These menwould not have been <i> qualified</text> without God inspiring them)</text> 
<text class='p'><b> Signifies</b> to be an indication of, mean.  Tomake known as by a sign.</text> 
<text class='p'><b> Inspiration</b> the wordinspiration literally means <i> God breathed</text> .  It refers to the Divineauthority of the Scriptures.</text> 
<text class='p'><b> Canonicity –</b> the process of the books of theBible being gathered together in their current form.</text> 
<text class='p'><b> Unction–</b> literally means to smearwith oil, it refers to the power of the Holy Ghost to enable a man to preachthe Gospel.</text> 
<text class='p'><b> Sanctification–</b> the process of beingseparated or set apart for God.</text> 
<text class='p'><b> Salvation–</b> takes in the meaning ofsafety, preservation, and deliverance. Itrefers to the Divine act of God converting a sinner to one who is saved or asaint.</text> 
<text class='p'><b> Justification–</b> means to be set in a rightrelationship with God. Itis just as if I had never sinned.</text> 
<text class='p'><b> Regeneration</b> is The Divine act whichimparts to The penitent believer The new and higher life in personal union withChrist.</text> 









<text class='h1'>Work Section of Textbook</text> 

<text class='p'>WORK SECTION 1:  <i> Introduction &amp; General Details ofthe Bible</text>  (Pages 2-15)</text> 

<text class='p'>Bible Journal</text> 

<text class='p'>You willcreate a "Bible Journal" throughout the course of the year.  It will be checkedfor progress at Lessons 9 &amp; 18 and will be handed in completed by thelesson before your final exam.  Your journal should be a spiral single subjectnotebook.  You will use this notebook ONLY for your Bible Journal.  There are 66books in the Bible and so your journal will have 66 entries.  You should make <b></text>  entries per week.  Each entry should be a personal application orrevelation related to each book of the Bible.</text> 

<text class='p'>For example:</text> 
<text class='p'>.........</text> 
<text class='p'>  Journal Entry 1: October 12, 2045:</text>  Genesis 15:4 &lt;&lt;followed by 50 to 100 words relatedto the text chosen&gt;&gt; <i> Before today, I never really saw this verse thisway...</text> 
<text class='p'>  Journal Entry 2: October 15, 2045:</text>  Exodus 20:17 &lt;&lt;followed by 50 to 100 words relatedto the text chosen&gt;&gt;  <i> The Lord really made this clear to me today</text> 










<text class='p'> Study Questions 1: Introduction &amp;General Details of the Bible</text> 

<text class='p'>Whatis the Bible? The Bible is God's ....  writtenRevelation of His will to men.</text> 

<text class='p'>There are __  __ books inthe entire Bible.</text> 
<text class='p'>There are __  __ books inthe Old Testament.</text> 
<text class='p'>There are __  __ books inthe New Testament.</text> 

<text class='p'>What does the word   Bible mean and why are its writingscalled the Bible?</text> 
<text class='p'> The word Bible means books.  Its writings are referred to as the Biblebecause they are a collection of books.</text> 

<text class='p'>What are some of the Bible's own names for itself? (at least 3)</text> 
<text class='p'> The Book Testament Scripture The Word of God</text> 

<text class='p'>What was the original language of the Old Testament?</text> 
<text class='p'> The original language of the Old Testament was Hebrew with a littleAramaic.</text> 
<text class='p'>What was the original language of the New Testament?</text> 
<text class='p'> The original language of the New Testament was Greek.</text> 
<text class='p'>Give three comparisons from your notes between the Old and NewTestaments.</text> 
<text class='p'> Both 1)begin with Divinity 2) share the same theme 3)center on Christ</text> 

<text class='p'>List the 10 commandments in their order found in Exodus 20.</text> 
<text class='p'> Churchesneed leadership, equity, and order.</text> <div class=WordSection7> 
<text class='p'>1-  Thou shalt have no other gods before me.</text> 
<text class='p'>2-  hou shalt not make untothee any graven image</text> 
<text class='p'>3-  Thou shalt not takethe name of the LORD thy God in vain.</text> 

<text class='p'>4-  Remember the sabbathday, to keep it holy.</text> 

<text class='p'>5-  Honour thy father and thy mother.</text> 
<text class='p'>6-  Thou shalt not kill</text> 
<text class='p'>7-  Thou shalt not commit adultery.</text> 
<text class='p'>8-  Thou shalt not steal.</text> 
<text class='p'>9-  Thou shalt not bear false witness against thy neighbour.</text> 
<text class='p'>10-  Thou shalt not covet any thing that is thy neighbour's.</text> </text> <div class=WordSection8> 

<text class='p'>What books are the "GOSPELS"?</text> 
<text class='p'> Matthew, Mark, Luke,John</text> 

<text class='p'>Give in brief 5 reasons from your notes why the Bible was written:</text> 
<text class='p'> The Bible was written that men might believe, understand, know, love, and follow Christ.</text> 

<text class='p'>Describe any 5 principal places of the Bible.</text> 
<text class='p'>Describe any 5 characters of the Bible.</text> 
<text class='p'>List 10 principal events of the Bible:</text> 

<text class='p'>Which book of the Bible describes the rebuilding ofJerusalem's walls?</text> 
<text class='p'>Nehemiah</text> 

<text class='p'>Which book is a poem symbolizing the love of Christ and HisBride?</text> 
<text class='p'>Song of Solomon</text> 

<text class='p'>Which book represents Christ as the compassionate friend ofsinners?</text> 
<text class='p'>Luke</text> 

<text class='p'>Where was John when he received his "revelation"?</text> 
<text class='p'>Imprisoned on the Isleof Patmos in AD 100.</text>  </text> 






<text class='p'>  Quiz 1: Introduction &amp; General Details of theBible</text> 
<text class='p'>Whatis the Bible? The Bible is God's .... writtenRevelation of His will to men.</text> 

<text class='p'>There are __  __ books inthe entire Bible.</text> 
<text class='p'>There are __  __ books inthe Old Testament.</text> 
<text class='p'>There are __  __ books inthe New Testament.</text> 

<text class='p'>What does the word  <i> Bible</i>  mean and why are its writingscalled the Bible?</text> 
<text class='p'>The word Bible means books.  Its writings are referred to as the Biblebecause they are a collection of books.</text> 
<text class='p'>What are some of the Bible's own names for itself? (at least 3)</text> 
<text class='p'>The Book Testament Scripture The Word of God</text> 
<text class='p'>What was the original language of the New Testament?</text> 
<text class='p'>The original language of the New Testament was Greek.</text> 
<text class='p'>8-17. List the 10 commandments in their orderfound in Exodus 20.</text> 
<text class='p'>Thou shalt have no other godsbefore me.</text> 
<text class='p'>houshalt not make unto thee any graven image</text> 
<text class='p'>Thou shalt not take the name of theLORD thy God in vain.</text> 
<text class='p'>Remember the sabbath day, to keepit holy.</text> 
<text class='p'>Honour thy father and thy mother.</text> 
<text class='p'>Thou shalt not kill</text> 
<text class='p'>Thou shalt not commit adultery.</text> 
<text class='p'>Thou shalt not steal.</text> 
<text class='p'>Thou shalt not bear false witnessagainst thy neighbour.</text> 
<text class='p'>Thou shalt not covet any thing thatis thy neighbour's.</text> 

<text class='p'>Give in brief 2 reasons from yournotes why the Bible was written : . )</text> 
<text class='h2'>The Bible was writtenthat men might believe, understand, know, love, and follow Christ.</text> 

<text class='p'>Which book is a poem symbolizing the love ofChrist and His Bride?  Song of Solomon</text> 









<text class='p'>  Study Questions 2: Perfect Unity of theBible</text> 

<text class='p'>What is redemption an act of?</text> 
<text class='p'>Redemption is the act of purchasing or paying in full.</text> 

<text class='p'>How as manbeen redeemed?</text> 
<text class='p'>By the blood of Jesus Christ.</text> 

<text class='p'>What isthe main theme of the Bible?</text> 
<text class='p'>Salvation through the blood of Jesus.</text> 

<text class='p'>ExplainGenesis 3:15.</text> 
<text class='p'>This is a prophecy that the Messiah who would come from the seed of thewoman would one day bruise the head of the serpent.</text> 
<text class='p'>Who is themain person of the Bible?</text> 
<text class='p'>Jesus Christ the Redeemer is the main person of the Bible.</text> 

<text class='p'>Can Jesusbe seen in any way in the Old Testament? How or why not?</text> 
<text class='p'>Yes, Jesus is seen in the Old Testament in type and prophecy as thecoming Messiah.</text> 

<text class='p'>Can true science prove the Bible wrong? Explain your answer.</text> 
<text class='p'>There is nocontradiction between true science and the Bible.</text> 

<text class='p'>What does it mean to say "THE BIBLE IS THE  <i> INFALLIBLE</text>  WORD OFGOD"?</text> 
<text class='p'>It means there is no contradiction, mistake or failure in the Bible.  It is absolutely trustworthy.</text> 
<text class='p'>In what four ways is the Bible "ONE"?</text> 
<text class='p'>It is one in PROPHECY - DOCTRINE -PURPOSE - STRUCTURE.</text> 

<text class='p'>Complete the following statement: There is but one Bible composed of...</text> 
<text class='p'>Both Old and NewTestaments.</text> 
<text class='p'>What is so remarkableabout t the way in which the Bible was    written</text> ?</text> 
<text class='p'>It was written by overforty writers who lived over a period of at least 1600 years in about 13different countries and on 3 continents who wrote from vastly differentbackgrounds!</text> 







<text class='p'>  Quiz 2: Perfect Unity of the Bible</text> 

<text class='p'>What is redemption an act of?</text>  
<text class='p'>Redemption is the act of purchasing or paying in full.</text> 

<text class='p'>How as manbeen redeemed?</text> 
<text class='p'>By the blood of Jesus Christ.</text> 

<text class='p'>What isthe main theme of the Bible?</text> 
<text class='p'>Salvation through the blood of Jesus.</text> 

<text class='p'>ExplainGenesis 3:15.</text> 
<text class='p'>This is a prophecy that the Messiah who would come from the seed of thewoman would one day bruise the head of the serpent.</text> 
<text class='p'>Who is themain person of the Bible?</text> 
<text class='p'>Jesus Christ the Redeemer is the main person of the Bible.</text> 

<text class='p'>Can Jesusbe seen in any way in the Old Testament? How or why not?</text> 
<text class='p'>Yes, Jesus is seen in the Old Testament in type and prophecy as thecoming Messiah.</text> 

<text class='p'>Can true science prove the Bible wrong? Explain your answer.</text> 
<text class='p'>There is nocontradiction between true science and the Bible.</text> 

<text class='p'>What does it mean to say "THE BIBLE IS THE  <i> INFALLIBLE</text>  WORD OFGOD"?</text> 
<text class='p'>It means there is nocontradiction, mistake or failure in the Bible.  It is absolutely trustworthy.</text> 
<text class='p'>In what four ways is the Bible "ONE"?</text> 
<text class='p'>It is one in PROPHECY - DOCTRINE -PURPOSE - STRUCTURE.</text> 

<text class='p'>Complete the following statement: There is but one Bible composed of...</text> 
<text class='p'>Both Old and NewTestaments.</text> 
<text class='p'>What is so remarkableabout t the way in which the Bible was    written</text> ?</text> 







<text class='p'>Study Questions 3: Inspiration of the Bible</text> 

<text class='p'>What is the Greek word and literal translation of the phrase  <i> given by inspiration of God</text> ? (2 Tim.  3:16)</text> 
<text class='p'>TheGreek word is ‘theopneustos' and literally means  <i> God breathed</text> .</text> 

<text class='p'>If the Bible is not the product of men,how did it come about? What is its origin?</text> 
<text class='p'>TheHoly Ghost breathed the Word into men who were human tools of the DivineAuthor.</text> 

<text class='p'>Do we have an inspired Word of God? Whatmust every believer undoubtedly know?</text> 
<text class='p'>Yes,we have an inspired Word of God and every Believer must know beyond all doubtthat their Bible is none other than the breath of the Almighty God.</text> 

<text class='p'> List 4 false views on Biblical inspiration and give a briefexplanation of each one:</text> 
<text class='p'>  VEIW 1</text> :  The Bible wasproduced by natural inspiration.</text> 
<text class='p'>EXPLAIN:  This view holds thatthe Bible is merely the product of genius of a high order, but not a product ofthe supernatural or Divine.  (Such as the geniuses of Milton, Shakespeare, orConfucius. )</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>  VEIW 2</text> :  God used levelsof inspiration to give us the Bible.</text> 
<text class='p'>EXPLAIN:  This view claims that God sometimesused ‘divine inspiration' and at other times merely offered suggestions orpromptings.</text> 

<text class='p'>  VEIW 3</text> :  God only gavethe concepts or thoughts to the men who wrote the Bible.</text> 
<text class='p'>EXPLAIN:  This view leaves thewording of the text to the minds of men.</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>  VEIW 4</text> :  Only portionsof the Bible are inspired.</text> 
<text class='p'>EXPLAIN:  This view claims the Bible ‘contains'the Word of God, but is not entirely divinely inspired.</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>What is the correct understanding ofBiblical inspiration?</text> 
<text class='p'>"Verbaland plenary inspiration" is the correct view.</text> 

<text class='p'>To what extent does the Bible claiminspiration? (Give Scripture reference. )</text> 
<text class='p'>Theentire Bible is inspired.  (2 Timothy 3:16)</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>What does infallible mean?</text> 
<text class='p'>Infalliblemeans  <i> to be totally exempt from the possibility of mistake</text> .</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>Who wrote Scripture?  (GiveScripture verse verbatim. )</text> 
<text class='p'>Holymen, moved upon, driven by the prompting of the Holy Ghost wrote Scripture.</text> 
<text class='p'>2 Peter 1:21— <i> For the prophecy came not in old time by thewill of man: but holy men of God spake as they were moved</text> <i>  by the HolyGhost</text> <i> .</text>   <i></text> 

<text class='p'>WORK SECTION 3, Part B</text> 

<text class='p'>Choose a Scripture of your own that illustrates the significanceof the ‘letters' of Scripture being inspired.  (Use another example other thanthe one included in the textbook. ) VARIOUS EXAMPLES.</text> 

<text class='p'>Explain the peculiar terminology in Matthew 5:18.</text> 
<text class='p'>A jotcould be equaled by an apostrophe and a tittle equaled by a hyphen.</text> 

<text class='p'>According to Dan Burgon, "Everybook of it, every chapter,every verse, every word, every syllable, every letter is..." what?</text> 
<text class='p'>Thedirect utterance of the Most High.</text> 

<text class='p'>Identify each man with the Scripture verse they each testified to as pivotal to their conversions: A)John 3:16 B)Isaiah 53:5C)Galatians 3:11 D)Isaiah 45:22</text> 
<text class='p'><img width=37 height=2 src="bibleintro%20temp_files/image010. png">   <u></text>  John Calvin</text> 
<text class='p'><img width=37 height=2 src="bibleintro%20temp_files/image011. png">   <u></text>  Spurgeon</text> 
<text class='p'><img width=37 height=2 src="bibleintro%20temp_files/image010. png">   <u></text>  Martin Luther</text> 
<text class='p'><img width=37 height=2 src="bibleintro%20temp_files/image011. png">   A</text>  Robert Moffat&amp; Richard Weaver</text> 

<text class='p'>What influence or effects can the Word of God have on aperson?</text> 
<text class='p'>Produces born again men, produces spiritual growth, cleans lives, builds up the Believer and ends or culminates its work in perfection.</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>What type of unity does Bible have?</text> 
<text class='p'>TheBible has unbroken and Perfect Unity.</text> 

<text class='p'>Where in the Bible would one turn to find earmarks of theselast days foretold? (1 reference)</text> 
<text class='p'>Daniel12; Matthew 24; 2 Timothy 3 &amp; 4; Luke 17.</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>19) Givethe definition for peerless.</text> 
<text class='p'>Having no equal</text> 

<text class='p'> Howaccurate are the prophecies in the Bible? Explain your logic.</text> 
<text class='p'>Every prophecy in the Bible is 100% accurate. No prophetic utterance of the Bible has missed its mark.  For example, Christfulfilled every prophecy concerning Him to totality.</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>Comment on the historical accuracy of Scripture.  (3-5 sentences minimum)</text> 

<text class='p'> Expoundon the thought "The Peerless Power of the Bible. " (8-10 sentences)</text> 









<text class='p'>  Quiz 3: Inspiration of the Bible</text> 

<text class='p'>What isthe Greek word and literal translation of the phrase  <i> given by inspiration ofGod</text> ? (2 Tim.  3:16)</text> 
<text class='p'>TheGreek word is ‘theopneustos' and literally means  <i> God breathed</text> .</text> 

<text class='p'>If theBible is not the product of men, how did it come about? What is its origin?</text> 
<text class='p'>TheHoly Ghost breathed the Word into men who were human tools of the DivineAuthor.</text> 

<text class='p'>Do we havean inspired Word of God? What must every believer undoubtedly know?</text> 
<text class='p'>Yes,we have an inspired Word of God and every Believer must know beyond all doubtthat their Bible is none other than the breath of the Almighty God.</text> 

<text class='p'> List atleast 3 of 4 false views on Biblical inspiration.</text> 
<text class='p'>  VEIW 1</text> :  The Bible was produced bynatural inspiration.</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>  VEIW 2</text> :  God used levels ofinspiration to give us the Bible.</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>  VEIW 3</text> :  God only gave the conceptsor thoughts to the men who wrote the Bible</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>  VEIW 4</text> :  Only portions of the Bibleare inspired.</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>What is thecorrect understanding of Biblical inspiration?</text> 
<text class='p'>"Verbaland plenary inspiration" is the correct view.</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>Who wroteScripture? (Give Scripture verse verbatim. )</text> 
<text class='p'>Holymen, moved upon, driven by the prompting of the Holy Ghost wrote Scripture.</text> 
<text class='p'>2 Peter 1:21— <i> For the prophecy came not in old time bythe will of man: but holy men of God spake as they were moved</text> <i>  by the HolyGhost.</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>According to Dan Burgon,"Everybook of it, every chapter, every verse, every word, every syllable, everyletter is..." what?</text> 
<text class='p'>Thedirect utterance of the Most High.</text> 

<text class='p'>What influence or effects can theWord of God have on a person? (at least 3)</text> 
<text class='p'>Producesborn again men, produces spiritual growth, cleans lives, builds up the Believerand ends or culminates its work in perfection.</text> 

<text class='p'>Where in the Bible would one turnto find earmarks of these last days foretold? (1 reference)</text> 
<text class='p'>Daniel12; Matthew 24; 2 Timothy 3 &amp; 4; Luke 17.</text> 

<text class='p'>BONUS:Expound on the thought "The Peerless Power of th e Bible. " (at least 5sentences)</text> 











<text class='p'> Study Questions 4: Canonization of the Bible</text> 
<text class='p'>What are the five categories of the NT canon?</text> 
<text class='h3'>  Gospels</text> <i> Matthew, Mark, Luke, John</text> 
<text class='h3'>  History</text> <i> Acts</text> 
<text class='h3'>  PaulineEpistles</text> <i> Romans, 1&amp;2Corinthians, Galatians, Ephesians, Philippians, Colossians, 1&amp;2Thessalonians, 1&amp;2 Timothy, Titus, Philemon,</text> <i> Hebrews*</text> 
<text class='h3'>  General Epistles</text> <i> (Hebrews*) James, I&amp;2 Peter, 1,2&amp;3 John, Jude</text> 
<text class='h3'>  Prophecy</text> <i> Revelation</text> 
<text class='p'>What does  <i> TextusReceptus</text>  mean?</text> 
<text class='p'>The Latin phrase  <i> TextusReceptus</text>  means  <i> Received Text and refers to</text> the Greek New Testamentmanuscripts as they were commonly accepted by the early church.</text> 
<text class='p'>COMPLETETHE FOLLOWING: There is a _____________ _____________ ______________of the ______________________ text that was commonly accepted by the earlychurch. (clear traceable stream, inspired. )</text> 

<text class='p'>What percentage of the existing Greek manuscripts agree with the KJV and Erasmus'own Greek NT?</text> 
<text class='p'>99 % of over 5,200manuscripts of the Greek New Testament agree with the KJV and Erasmus' Greek New Testament.</text> 

<text class='p'>Whoprinted the first Greek NT and when did he do it?</text> 
<text class='p'>Erasmuspublished a Greek New Testament text in 1516.</text> 

<text class='p'>Explainthis printer's method of deciding what his NT would say.  (2 to 3 sentences)</text> 
<text class='p'>He used every manuscriptavailable and compared them with great care to insure a correct Greek NewTestament would be printed and circulated for the first time.</text> 

<text class='p'>Summarizein one sentence Mr.  Kenneth W.  Clark's comments concerning the creation of the  <i> TextusReceptus</text> .</text> 
<text class='p'>"We should notattribute to Erasmus the creation of a ‘received text,' but only thetransmission from a manuscript text, already commonly received, to a    printed</text>   form</text> , in which this text would continue to prevail for three centuries. "</text> 

<text class='p'>Writeverbatim and memorize I Peter 1:23.</text> 
<text class='p'>1Pe 1:23 Being bornagain, not of corruptible seed, but of incorruptible, by the word of God, whichliveth and abideth for ever.</text> 
<text class='p'>What twoearly church leaders were tutored by the Apostle John?</text> 
<text class='p'>Ignatius andPolycarp, leaders of the early church, were taught by the Apostle John</text> 
<text class='p'>What NT books were firstassembled together as a collection?</text> 
<text class='p'>The first New Testamentbooks to be assembled together were the Epistles of Paul.</text> 

<text class='p'>By what date was there acomplete Biblical canon assembled of 27 books?</text> 
<text class='p'>300 AD</text> 
<text class='p'>What Scripture referenceattests to the fact that Paul's epistles are Scripture?</text> 
<text class='p'>II Peter 3:15,16</text> 

<text class='p'>Who first used the phrase"New Testament" referring to the second half of books of the Bible?</text> 
<text class='p'>Tertullian</text> 
<text class='p'>List fives tests (questions) for NT canonicity.</text> 
<text class='h3'>Was the book written by an Apostle?</text> 
<text class='h3'>Was the book approved by an apostle?</text> 
<text class='h3'>Was the book universally accepted by the early church bythe end of the fourth century?</text> 
<text class='h3'>Wasthe book read publicly when the early church gathered for the Lord's Supper?</text> 
<text class='h3'>Wasthe book consistent with the rest of accepted Scripture?</text> 

<text class='p'>What do  <i> Homologoumena</text> and  <i> Antilegomena</text>  mean?</text> 
<text class='h3'>  Homologoumena</text>  means  <i> acknowledged</text>  and refers to the readilyaccepted books of the New Testament.  Twenty out of the twenty-seven books ofthe New Testament were readily and universally accepted as genuine, and calledthe Homologoumena.  These twenty books were the four Gospels, the Acts, theepistles of Paul (except Hebrews), and the first epistles of John and Peter.</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='h3'>  Antilegomena</text>  means  <i> disputed</text>  and refers to the books that werenot readily accepted by the church leaders and took more time to be acceptedinto the Canon of Scripture. The seven books were Hebrews, II and III John, IIPeter, Jude, James, Revelation.  These were disputed for a time and called theAntilegomena</text> 
<text class='p'>Explain what the Apocryphal writings are.  (2-5 sentences)</text> 
<text class='h3'>TheApocrypha generally refers to the books placed between the Old and NewTestaments and included as an addendum to some Canons.  These books derive theirname from a Greek word,  <i> apokruphos</text> , which means hidden.  They are calledthis because they are hidden and of unknown authority.  The Roman CatholicChurch accepts the Apocrypha as part of their Canon of Scripture.</text> 

<text class='p'>What are Pseudepigraphicalwritings?</text> 
<text class='h3'>Thisis a term applied to books deemed non canonical but claiming some kind ofreligious authenticity or value.  Some of the books in this category were deemedforgeries claiming Apostolic origin such as the Gospel according to Thomas.</text> 
<text class='p'>Compare the recognized true canon of Scripture with the Roman Catholiccanon.</text> 
<text class='p'>The Roman Catholic Church includes the 66 books of ourBible and also accepts the Apocrypha as part of their Canon of Scripture.  Thisis the same Canon as Jerome's who produced the Latin Vulgate which is the basisfor the Roman Catholic Bible.</text> 










<text class='p'>  Quiz 4: Canonization of the Bible</text> 
<text class='p'>What does  <i> Textus Receptus</text>  mean?</text> 
<text class='p'>What percentage of the existing Greek manuscripts agree with the KJV andErasmus' own Greek NT?</text> 
<text class='p'>Who printed the first Greek NT and when did he do it?</text> 
<text class='p'>Summarize in one sentence Mr.  Kenneth W.  Clark's comments concerning thecreation of the  <i> Textus Receptus</text> .</text> 
<text class='p'>Write verbatim and memorize I Peter 1:23.</text> 
<text class='p'>What two early church leader were tutored by the Apostle John?</text> 
<text class='p'>By what date was there a complete Biblical canon assembled of 27 books?</text> 
<text class='p'>What Scripture reference attests to the fact that Paul's epistles areScripture?</text> 
<text class='p'>Who first used the phrase "New Testament" referring to the second halfof books of the Bible?</text> 
<text class='p'>What do  <i> Homologoumena</text>  and  <i> Antilegomena</text>  mean?</text> 
<text class='p'>Explain what the Apocryphal writings are.  (2-5 sentences)</text> 
<text class='p'>Whatare Pseudepigraphical writings?</text> 







 

<text class='p'>  Study Questions 5: God's Word into English</text> 

<text class='p'>What does the word translation mean as it relatesto God's Word into English?</text> 
<text class='p'>The word translation means that which isproduced by turning words and phrases  from one language intoanother language.</text> 
<text class='p'>Which Bible version is referred to as theAuthorized Version?</text> 
<text class='p'>The King James Version is also called theAuthorized Version.</text> 
<text class='p'>Did Erasmus create the  <i> Textus Receptus?</text> 
<text class='p'>No, Erasmus did not create the  <i> TextusReceptus,</text>  but merely compiled and edited what had already beenreceived by the church when he published the first printed  Greek New Testament text in 1516.</text> 
<text class='p'>What three predecessors of modern Englishlanguages did the Bible exist in?</text> 
<text class='p'>Gothic , Anglo- Saxon, and Middle English</text> 
<text class='p'>What country surprisingly fought the translationof the Bible into the English  language?</text> 
<text class='p'>England itself fought the translation of theBible into the English language.</text> 
<text class='p'>How many of the English Bibles that predate theKJV has been in agreement  with the Received Text?</text> 
<text class='p'>All of the English Bibles that predate the KJVhave been in agreement with the  Received Text.</text> 
<text class='p'>Did Wycliffe use Jerome's Latin Vulgate for histranslation?</text> 
<text class='p'>No, Wycliffe did not use Jerome's Latin Vulgatefor his translation.</text> 
<text class='p'>Which Latin source did Wycliffe use for histranslation?</text> 
<text class='p'>Wycliffe  recordsin his preface that he translated from the vulgar Latin which  werethe old Latin manuscripts in the common tongue of the people.</text> 
<text class='p'>What was the first printed edition of the NewTestament in the English language?</text> 
<text class='p'>The Tyndale New Testament was the first printededition in the English language.</text> 
<text class='p'>What was  Tyndale's finalprayer before he was burned at the stake?</text> 
<text class='p'>Tyndale's final prayerbefore he was burned at the stake was: O Lord, open the <i></text> Kingof England's eyes.</text> 

<text class='p'>What was  thefirst English Bible authorized for public use?</text> 
<text class='p'>The Great Bible was the first English Bibleauthorized for public use.</text> 
<text class='p'>How did the Geneva Bible acquire its name?</text> 
<text class='p'>The Geneva Bible is so named because it wasproduced in Geneva by the exiles  from England.</text> 

<text class='p'>Why was the Bishop's Bible produced?</text> 
<text class='p'>The Bishops' Bible was produced to conform tothe structure of the Church of  England, and to stand against thefalse notes of Calvanisim contained in the  Geneva Bible.</text> 
<text class='p'>What type of men did King James seek to do thetranslation work?</text> 
<text class='p'>King James sought outthe best qualified men.  These men were the best Biblical  scholarsand language experts of their day.</text> 

<text class='p'>According to the rules of translation who were theBishops to seek out to aid in  the translation process?</text> 
<text class='p'>The bishops were also asked to obtain the helpof the clergy and anyone who  was skilled in languages to aid in thetranslation process.</text> 
<text class='p'>In what year was the King James Version firstprinted?</text> 
<text class='p'>The KJV was first printed in 1611.</text> 
<text class='p'>Were there any actual revisions to the original1611 King James Version which  were published as the KJV?</text> 
<text class='p'>No, there were no actual revisions to theoriginal 1611 KJV.</text> 
<text class='p'>What were the three reasons for the subsequentprintings of the KJV since 1611?</text> 
<text class='p'>The 3 reasons were to change the font style, tocorrect typographical printing  errors, and to standardize thespelling.</text> 
<text class='p'>What English Bible is the pure Word of Godpreserved in the English language?</text> 
<text class='p'>The King James Version is the pure Word of Godpreserved in the English  language.</text> 
<text class='p'>How do YOU know the KJV is the pure Word of God?</text> 
<text class='p'>(Answer in your own words)</text>  </text> 










<text class='p'>  Quiz 5: God's Word into English</text> 

 

 
 

<text class='p'>  Study Questions 6: Modern Versions of the Bible</text> 
 </text> 






<text class='h1'>Final Exam</text> 

<text class='p'>There are __ <u></text> __ books inthe entire Bible.</text> 
<text class='p'>There are __ <u></text> __ books inthe Old Testament.</text> 
<text class='p'>There are __ <u></text> __ books inthe New Testament.</text> 

<text class='p'>What does the word  <i> Bible</text>  mean and why are its writingscalled the Bible?</text> 
<text class='p'>The word Bible means books. Its writings are referred to as the Bible because they are a collection ofbooks.</text> 
<text class='p'>What was the original language of the New Testament?</text> 
<text class='p'>The original language of theNew Testament was Greek.</text> 
<text class='p'>What is the main theme of the Bible?</text> 
<text class='p'>Salvation through the blood of Jesus.</text> 

<text class='p'>Explain Genesis 3:15.</text> 
<text class='p'>This is a prophecy that the Messiah who would come from theseed of the woman would one day bruise the head of the serpent.</text> 
<text class='p'>Can true science prove the Bible wrong? Explain your answer.</text> 
<text class='p'>There is no contradiction between true science and theBible.</text> 
<text class='p'><u></text> 
<text class='p'>What does it mean to say "THE BIBLE IS THE  <i> INFALLIBLE</text>  WORDOF GOD"?</text> 
<text class='p'>It means there is no contradiction, mistake or failure inthe Bible.  It is absolutely trustworthy.</text> 
<text class='p'>Whatis the Greek word and literal translation of the phrase  <i> given by inspirationof God</text> ? (2 Tim.  3:16)</text> 
<text class='p'>The Greek word is ‘theopneustos' and literally means  <i> Godbreathed</text> .</text> 
<text class='p'>Do we have an inspired Word of God? What must everybeliever undoubtedly know?</text> 
<text class='p'>Yes, we have an inspired Word of God and every Believermust know beyond all doubt that</text> 
<text class='p'>What does  <i> Textus Receptus</text>  mean?</text> 

<text class='p'>What percentage of the existing Greek manuscripts agreewith the KJV and Erasmus' own Greek NT?</text> 


<text class='p'>What two early church leader were tutored by the ApostleJohn?</text> 

<text class='p'>By what date was there a complete Biblical canon assembled of 27 books?</text> 

<text class='p'>  BONUS:</text> 

<text class='p'>What do  <i> Homologoumena</text>  and  <i> Antilegomena</text>  mean?</text> 


<text class='p'>Explain what the Apocryphal writings are.  (2-5 sentences)</text>
</div>
</div>
</document>